In this video, I'll be talking to you about substitution, so proofs by substitution, which
is another basic, very basic and elementary way of proving things.
So basically, what I'm doing in these few videos, so the theory behind proving something by substitution
is the following, suppose we have a theorem saying, let's say, that X equals Y, okay? Or
like, not X equals Y, I would just use like a mixture of Isabelle and Isabelle notation,
so for all X, let's make it more concrete, maybe, so let's say that this, like we have
a theorem that says that X, for all X, if you have an X and you add a Y to it, then you can
substitute that with a Y and an X, so for any X and Y, X plus Y equals Y plus X, which is
a commutativity of addition, suppose we have that.
Suppose we have, so if we have a theorem saying that, and we have a goal saying, let's say,
so I will just use the same notation, so goal saying 1 plus 3 is greater than or equal
to 3 plus 1, then we can substitute that lemma, which I'll call here lemma 1, for example, in
the goal, and from that we get a new goal, which says that 3 plus 1 is greater than or
equal to 3 plus 1, and so that basically is the, these are the mechanics of the operation.
So when does it make sense?
If the right-hand side of the lemma, and I will just call this any lemma of that form,
I'll just call these, which is the standard name in Isabelle, in Isabelle literature, so
I'll call this, if the right-hand side of the simplification rule, this improve for short,
is simpler than the LHS, or optimally, even if we already have a proof of the right-hand
side.
Okay, so that basically is the mechanic, this is the mechanics, then I will just show you
how to do like a simple proof example here on the board as usual, and then on Isabelle.
So let's say the following, so I will do the same thing, we will have like a theorem statement,
and then we will need to come up with the lemmas, to guess some lemmas basically, and
then use those lemmas to prove that theorem, in this case, this will just be proved by only
substitution, okay?
So let's say, so example, suppose we want to prove that x plus y times a plus b, or all
these are natural numbers, equals x times a plus x times b plus y times a plus y times
b, these are all natural numbers, so okay, so what's, what is the first step of the proof
here?
So let's say one, for example, so earlier when we did backward and forward reasoning,
we would take the assumptions and then go forward from them, but here we will take one side of
the equation and then keep substituting and changing it by substituting, so I'll just
say, let's just take the left-hand side, so we say x plus y times a plus b, then what?
How can we proceed?
So we will, we will basically, I'll just write down the steps, which are very simple, and
then we can figure out the, the, the, the lemmas that are needed to do those steps.
So if we say x plus y, x plus y, if we want to simplify that expression, we would just
use the normal distributivity law of addition, so we then get an x plus y, x plus y times
a plus x plus y times b, so here what's the lemma here that we use, so this is just using
distributivity and then we can then further analyze that, so we can take the right-hand
side of the previous equation, say x plus y times a plus x plus y times b, again we apply
the left distributivity, so we then have an x, so, so let's just write distributivity lemmas
explicitly so that it's clear what's going on, so here, let me just, so we use, using
a lemma that says, for any x, like x times any, let's say, a plus b, this is the lemma,
basically, we just call this lemma 1 equals x times a plus x times b, so I'll just call
this lemma 1, right, and this is like a simplification rule, this is the left distributivity of addition
and then we can do the right distributivity of addition, so we can, for example, analyze
that, that part, x plus y times a, so we can say x, so we can say this equals x times a
plus y times a plus x plus y times b, and this is going to be using lemma 2, which is
a plus b times x equals a times x, for any, this is, of course, all of these are quantified,
so that's why we have the question marks, plus b times x, okay, and then we apply the
same lemma tool, so we get, we proceed with number, with step number 3, so we take that
right-hand side and I will just write dots here, and then I will say x times a plus y
times a plus x times b plus y times b, and that also is using, okay, and then we have
our proof, so here, as you can see, we just did three steps of substitution, both of them
are depending on those laws of addition, so that's very simple.